Guide to the Herman Benson Papers TAM.834
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Herman Benson Papers
1933-2009
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Association for Union Democracy
Benson, Herman W.
TAM.834
3.5 Linear Feet in 7 manuscript boxes
Herman Benson (1915-2020) was a machinist, labor organizer, union reformer, and one of the co-founders of the Association for Union Democracy (AUD). Benson, a life-long New Yorker, recognized that even democratic entities like organized labor and unions wrestled with accountability and corruption. He is well-known for his work to introduce democratic reforms to trade unions. In 1969 he co-founded the AUD and he became the editor for the AUD's newsletter Union Democracy Review. From their website, AUD is "the only national, pro-labor, non-profit organization dedicated solely to advancing the principles and practices of democratic trade unionism in the North American labor movement. It is the premise of AUD that internal democracy makes unions stronger and better able to fight for the rights and interests of working people." AUD is notable for its non-partisan positioning, and as such does not endorse candidates for union positions or specific policies within unions. The organization works to empower union members by focusing on active participation, strengthening the democratic process, and free speech and fair elections. The Herman Benson Papers (dated 1933-2009) consist of materials created and collected by Benson documenting his work with the Association for Union Democracy (AUD), as well his life-long study of labor, socialism, alternatives to capitalism, and democratic causes. Materials include notebooks, research notes, and original writings in various stages of completion. Some notebooks also include observations on a wide variety of topics, similar to a journal or a scrapbook. The collection also includes correspondence and photographs. In addition to documenting Benson's involvement with AUD, the materials in this collection more directly document his intellectual process and his study of labor, labor movements, unions, labor organizing, and socialism.
Scope and Contents
The Herman Benson Papers (dated 1933-2009) consist of materials created and collected by Benson documenting his work with the Association for Union Democracy (AUD), as well his life-long study of labor, socialism, alternatives to capitalism, and democratic causes. Materials include notebooks, research notes, and original writings in various stages of completion. Some notebooks also include observations on a wide variety of topics, similar to a journal or a scrapbook. The collection also includes correspondence and photographs. In addition to documenting Benson's involvement with AUD, the materials in this collection more directly document his intellectual process and his study of labor, labor movements, unions, labor organizing, and socialism.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the Association of Union Democracy in May 2024; the accession number associated with this purchase is 2024.029.
Biographical Note
Herman Benson (1915-2020) was a machinist, labor organizer, union reformer, and one of the co-founders of the Association for Union Democracy (AUD). Benson, a life-long New Yorker, recognized that even democratic entities like organized labor and unions wrestled with accountability and corruption. He is well-known for his work to introduce democratic reforms to trade unions. In 1969 he co-founded the AUD and he became the editor for the AUD's newsletter Union Democracy Review.
From their website, AUD is "the only national, pro-labor, non-profit organization dedicated solely to advancing the principles and practices of democratic trade unionism in the North American labor movement. It is the premise of AUD that internal democracy makes unions stronger and better able to fight for the rights and interests of working people." AUD is notable for its non-partisan positioning, and as such does not endorse candidates for union positions or specific policies within unions. The organization focuses its attention on empowering union members through active participation, strengthening the democratic process, and free speech and fair elections.
Source:
Association for Union Democracy. "About Us." Accessed May 31, 2024. https://uniondemocracy.org/about-us/
Labor; Labor leaders.; Labor movement.; Labor -- History; Labor union members.; Historians; Socialism; Labor union democracy.; Labor unions -- Organizing.; Association for Union Democracy
- Paul Buhle Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bukharin (Cohen), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "Credo" -- Research Files and Notes, 2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- SIU, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- John Dunlop Correspondence and Research, 1960-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Writings -- "The Uncertain Trumpet", undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- AUD and UDA, 1968-2004 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Dodge Main News, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- ISL, 1948-1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Research Files -- Socialism, 1933-2004 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
- Socialism, Religious, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Mumia Abu Jamal, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Clippings -- New York Times, 1981-1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Civil Liberties Forum, 1969-1995 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
- Fiction by Benson -- "Tips on Christmas", undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Research Files -- Germany, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Research Files -- Trotskyism, 1994-2007 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Writings -- Union Democracy, Three Secretaries of Labor, Union Reformers, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Research Files -- Donahue Debate Speech, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Research Files -- ACLU, 1949-2004 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Research Files -- United Worker's Movement, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Research, Writing, and Correspondence -- Socialism, 1991-2001 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Research Files -- Socialism, 1955-2008 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Joe Rauh Correspondence, Clippings, and Writing, 1973-1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Rebels, Reformers, and Racketeers -- Publisher Correspondence and Reviewer Feedback, 2001-2004 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Alec Note -- Research and Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- AJ Hayes -- Research and Notes, 1958-1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Writing Drafts -- "Public Employees", 1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Research Files -- Intellectuals, Union Democracy, Zieger, 1995-2002 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Research Files -- Intellectuals, Union Democracy, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Intellectuals -- University Periodicals, 1997-2011 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Research Files and Writings -- Intellectuals, 1959-2008 (Box 2, Folder 12-15)
- Research Files -- Theories, Analysis, Critics, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Research Files -- Theories, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Research Files -- Labor, 1957-1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Labor Management Reporting and Disclosure Act (LMRDA), 1959 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Research Files and Writings -- Union Democracy, 1955-1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Writings -- Drafts and Correspondence, 1998, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Rebels, Reformers, and Racketeers -- Reviews and Correspondence, 2004-2008 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Research Files -- Corruption, Union, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Research Files -- Dunlop et al, 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Research Files -- Elite/Vanguard, 1938-1972 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Writing Drafts -- "Fund for Republic -- Intellectualism", 1971-1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- "Drum" Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Speeches, 1982-2003 (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
- Research Files and Writing -- Labor History, 1958-1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Writings -- Painters in New York and California, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Writings -- Hayes Public Review Board, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Research Files -- Intellectuals (Attitude Toward Labor Movement), 1976-2010 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Research Files -- Theory on the Nature of the Labor Movement, 1958-1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Research Files -- Intellectuals, 1985-1998 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Research Files -- Fund for the Republic, 1958-1971 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
- Writings -- Harvard Text, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Research Binder -- "Intellectuals, 13", 1957-2001 (Box 4, Folder 10-12)
- Research Binder -- "Intellectuals, SAWSJ", 1973-2007 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Research Binder -- "Union Democracy, 12", 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Research Binder -- "Attempts to Define Socialism", 1985-2008 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Research Binder -- "New Strategies", 1958-2006 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
- Notebook 7, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Binder/Notebook -- "Random Notes, Words", 2009 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Binder/Notebook 2, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Binder/Notebook 8, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Binder/Notebook "Books 5", undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Binder -- Union Democracy, 1944-1959 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Research Binder -- "Elites, 17", undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Research Binder -- "Mills, Power, 20", undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Research Binder -- "Immigration, 21", 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Research Binder -- "Socialism, 16", 1986 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Research Binder -- "Intellectuals, 10", undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Research Binder -- "Miscellaneous, 11", 1985-1991 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Research Notebook Binder -- "Maritime Notes, 3", 1960 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Notebook Binder -- "Rackets", undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Photographs -- Tamiment Event, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Photographs -- Association for Union Democracy Meetings and Conferences, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Photographs -- Benson Speaking, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Photographs -- Events (Possibly Benson Retirement), 1985 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Photographs -- Association for Union Democracy Events, Unidentified, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Association for Union Democracy Clyde Summers Celebration Program, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Association for Union Democracy Women Conference Program, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Association for Union Democracy Logos, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Democratic Rights for Union Members Cover Mock-up, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Association for Union Democracy Event Flyers, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Photographs -- Conference Photographs, Construction Conference, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 10-13)
- Photographs -- Association for Union Democracy, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Photographs -- Events, undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Clippings -- Association for Union Democracy, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)